Williams Obstetrics.
Chapter 65: Dermatological Disorders.
Pregnancy-Specific Dermatoses Other Dermatological Conditions Dermatological Treatment References Pregnancy-Specific Dermatoses Four dermatoses considered unique to pregnancy are pemphigoid gestationis (PG), pruritic urticarial papules and plaques of pregnancy (PUPPP), atopic eruption of pregnancy (AEP), and intrahepatic cholestasis of pregnancy.
Descriptions of these are given in Table 65-1.
Their gross appearance can be similar to each other or to other skin disorders, and pruritus is a common feature.
Of these four, adverse fetal outcomes are linked only with PG and intrahepatic cholestasis.
The latter is discussed in detail in Chapter 58 (p. 1032).
It generally lacks primary skin lesions, but pruritus is usually associated with abnormally elevated serum bile acid levels and mildly increased hepatic transaminase levels.
Table 65-1.
Pregnancy-specific Dermatoses # Pemphigoid Gestationis.
In this rare autoimmune bullous disease, pruritic papules and urticarial plaques initially form.
Vesicles or bullae usually follow after 1 to 2 weeks.
Lesions frequently involve umbilicus and other skin surfaces but typically spare mucous membranes, scalp, and face .
Figure 65-1.
Pemphigoid gestationis.
A. Abdominal plaques classically involve the umbilicus.
B. Blistered lesions on the wrist and forearm.
Reproduced with permission from Dr. Kara Ehlers.
Previously termed herpes gestationis, PG is not related to the herpesvirus.
Instead, maternal immunoglobulin G (IgG) antibodies target collagen XVII found in the basement membrane of skin and amnionic epithelium (Kelly, 1988; Sadik, 2016).
Collagen XVII is also termed bullous pemphigoid 180 (BP180).
Autoantibody binding to BP180 activates complement to promote eosinophil chemotaxis to the antigen-antibody complexes.
Eosinophilic degranulation damages the dermal–epidermal junction and leads to blistering.
Pregnancy In most cases, PG develops during a first pregnancy.
Most subsequent pregnancies also are affected, usually earlier and more severely .
Additionally, other autoimmune diseases, especially Graves disease, are frequent in affected women (Jenkins, 1999; Shornick, 1992).
PG usually begins during the second or third trimester, but postpartum onset or exacerbation is common .
The disease course is often marked by antepartum flares and remissions.
In cases with early-onset and blistering, PG can be associated with preterm birth, oligohydramnios, and fetal-growth restriction (Al-Saif, 2016; Chi, 2009; Dabas, 2018).
One theory suggests mild placental insufficiency stems from IgG and complement deposition along the amnionic basement membrane .
Thus, surveillance for and management of these complications in affected pregnancies is reasonable.
In 5 to 10 percent of cases, IgG antibodies passively transfer from the mother to cause similar skin lesions in the newborn .
These eruptions in the neonate require only wound care and clear spontaneously within a few weeks as the passively acquired IgG levels drop.
After delivery, maternal lesions resolve without scarring, and most women are disease-free after 6 months .
In some, however, resolution is protracted.
Disease may be exacerbated during menses or by oral contraceptives (Fania, 2017; Semkova, 2009).
Diagnosis and Treatment Before bullae form, these lesions may resemble PUPPP.
Other diagnoses include bullous pemphigoid, pustular psoriasis, erythema multiforme, linear IgA bullous dermatosis, urticaria, dermatitis herpetiformis, allergic contact dermatitis, and AEP (Lipozenčić, 2012).
Potentially life-threatening druginduced blistering syndromes, such as Stevens-Johnson syndrome and toxic epidermal necrolysis, also must be excluded .
Diagnostically, immunofluorescent staining of a skin punch biopsy sample is the most accurate.
With this, C3 complement and sometimes IgG are seen deposited along the basement membrane between the epidermis and the dermis (Katz, 1976; Tani, 2015).
Circulating IgG antibodies against BP180 also can be detected in maternal serum using enzyme-linked
immunosorbent assay (ELISA) (Al Saif, 2017; Sitaru, 2004).
Pruritus with PG can be severe.
Early in its course, topical high-potency corticosteroids and oral antihistamines may be effective (p. 1158).
For refractory lesions, an oral corticosteroid is provided, and prednisone or prednisolone is preferable.
Either is inactivated by placental 11-βhydroxylase enzyme, which significantly lowers fetal exposure .
Oral prednisone, 0.5 to 1 mg/kg daily and gradually tapered to a maintenance dose, is one option.
In rare intractable cases, intravenous immunoglobulin (IVIG) therapy, cyclosporine, or plasmapheresis has been used (Huilaja, 2015; Marker, 2011; Yang, 2018).
Rituximab early in pregnancy also is described, but its later use carries the risk of transient newborn immunosuppression risks (Chakravarty, 2011; Tourte, 2017).
# Pruritic Urticarial Papules and Plaques of Pregnancy.
This common pregnancy-specific dermatosis is characterized by intensely pruritic, 1- to 2-mm erythematous papules that coalesce to form urticarial plaques.
Also known as polymorphic eruption of pregnancy, PUPPP usually appears late in pregnancy .
Rarely, onset is postpartum .
The rash affects the abdomen and proximal thighs in 97 percent of women .
Lesions often initially form within striae but spare periumbilical skin.
The face, palms, and soles are rarely involved .
It is more frequent in whites and nulliparas, those with multifetal gestation, and those carrying a male fetus .
PUPPP seldom recurs in subsequent pregnancies.
Its cause is unknown, but an autoimmune basis is not implicated (Ambros-Rudolph, 2011; Lawley, 1979).
Figure 65-2.
Pruritic urticarial papules and plaques of pregnancy (PUPPP) shows small papules on the buttock and proximal thigh and within abdominal striae.
PUPPP mimics several other skin eruptions.
Some include contact dermatitis, drug eruption, viral exanthem, insect bites, scabies infestation, pityriasis rosea, and the other pregnancy-specific dermatoses (Brandão, 2017).
Specifically, it may appear similar to early PG that has not yet blistered.
In unclear cases, skin biopsy and negative serum BP180 antibody levels help to differentiate the two.
Pruritus will usually respond to treatment with oral antihistamines, skin emollients, and topical corticosteroids .
A few women will need short-course systemic corticosteroids to relieve severe itching .
PUPPP carries no adverse pregnancy effects.
It usually resolves within several days following delivery and does not scar.
In 15 to 20 percent of women, however, symptoms persist for 2 to 4 weeks postpartum .
# Atopic Eruption of Pregnancy.
This umbrella term encompasses three conditions previously considered separately: eczema in pregnancy, prurigo of pregnancy, and pruritic folliculitis of pregnancy .
Two thirds of women with AEP have widespread eczematous changes, whereas the other third have papular lesions .
Diagnosis is greatly aided by a history of prior atopy and by rash characteristics.
As a group, these three pose no risk to the fetus .
Eczema in pregnancy appears as traditional eczema but with a pregnancy onset.
It is the most common pregnancy-specific dermatosis, and affected skin shows dry, thickened, scaly, red patches involving extremity flexures, nipples, neck, and face .
In contrast, prurigo of pregnancy, also known as prurigo gestationis, is characterized by 5- to 10mm, itchy, erythematous papules or nodules commonly found on the extensor surfaces and trunk.
Last, pruritic folliculitis of pregnancy is rare and notable for small, erythematous follicular papules and sterile pustules predominantly on the trunk.
Of AEP cases, 75 percent develop in the first or second trimesters .
All lesions usually resolve with delivery but may persist for up to 3 months postpartum.
Recurrence with subsequent pregnancies is variable but common.
Diagnosis is one of exclusion.
Biopsy findings and serology results specific for PG are negative (p. 1155).
Serum bile acid levels help exclude cholestasis of pregnancy.
Many women with eczema of pregnancy have elevated serum immunoglobulin E
IgE) levels .
For all three AEP manifestations, skin lesions and pruritus are usually controlled with chronic emollient use, as-needed oral antihistamines, and low- or moderate-potency topical corticosteroid preparations .
With the latter, twice-daily application is continued for several weeks to achieve improvement.
For maintenance, moisturizer alone or once- or twiceweekly topical corticosteroid use is reasonable.
For severe eczema, secondline agents include short-course ultrapotent topical corticosteroids.
In some cases, topical tacrolimus, narrow-band ultraviolet B therapy, an oral corticosteroid, or cyclosporine is required (Eichenfield, 2014; Vestergaard, 2019).
Other Dermatological Conditions.
# Acne Vulgaris.
This is a common chronic dermatosis that may worsen, improve, or remain stable during pregnancy.
In symptomatic gravidas, either 2.5- to 5-percent benzoyl peroxide or 15- to 20-percent azelaic acid is a suitable topical, antiinflammatory, comedolytic agent .
If needed, 5-percent benzoyl peroxide can instead be coupled with either topical erythromycin or clindamycin, and combined solutions are available.
In these combinations, benzoyl peroxide minimizes development of Propionibacterium acnes drug resistance .
Topical retinoids include tretinoin and adapalene.
Large studies have not found higher rates of major birth defects with their topical use (Jick, 1993; Shapiro, 1997).
However, these are probably best avoided during pregnancy, especially the first trimester (Kaplan, 2015; Panchaud, 2012).
The topical retinoid tazarotene is contraindicated.
For more severe cases, oral antibiotics that include erythromycin, azithromycin, cephalexin, or amoxicillin may be coupled with benzoyl peroxide.
Systemic antibiotics are ideally delayed until the second trimester, and therapy duration limited to 4 to 6 weeks .
Refractory cases often merit dermatological consultation.
Also, for severe cases, a short course of oral corticosteroid or intralesional injection is an option.
Of these, oral agents are delayed until after the first trimester due to the small risk for facial clefts .
# Psoriasis and Pustular Psoriasis of Pregnancy.
Psoriasis is a common dermatosis with a variable course during pregnancy, however, postpartum flares are common .
The National Psoriasis Foundation offers pregnancy guidelines .
Emollients alone are given initially, and low- or moderate-potency topical corticosteroids can be added.
In resistant cases, restrained use of highpotency or ultrapotent topical corticosteroids appears safe in the second and third trimesters.
Ultraviolet B phototherapy is a second-line option.
Last, cyclosporine, oral corticosteroids, or tumor necrosis factor alpha (TNF-α) antagonists that include adalimumab, etanercept, and infliximab are third-tier agents for pregnancy.
Overall, psoriasis itself does not pose a higher risk of adverse pregnancy outcomes .
With severe disease, a small increased risk of low birthweight, gestational diabetes, and preeclampsia was found by some (Bröms, 2018; Yang, 2011).
Psoriasis is most commonly of the chronic plaque variety.
In contrast, with pustular psoriasis of pregnancy, severe systemic symptoms may develop and can mimic sepsis.
Formerly called impetigo herpetiformis, this rare pustular form has an erythematous background and pruritic plaques ringed by sterile pustules that enlarge, coalesce, and then crust .
Plaques initially involve intertriginous areas but may spread to the torso, extremities, and oral mucosa.
Extensive lesions can lead to massive fluid loss with hypovolemia, placental insufficiency, and fetal compromise and may also become secondarily infected.
Figure 65-3.
Generalized pustular psoriasis of pregnancy displays erythematous, sometimes pruritic plaques ringed by sterile pustules that enlarge and then form a scaling crust.
Reproduced with permission from Dr. Paul Slocum.
Testing reveals leukocytosis, elevated erythrocyte sedimentation rate, hypocalcemia, and hypoalbuminemia .
Blood cultures and skin viral/bacterial cultures to exclude infection and a diagnostic
skin biopsy are obtained.
Classically, the former are sterile, and the latter reveals epidermal pustules of neutrophils.
First-line treatment is with oral prednisone (15–80 mg/d), cyclosporine (2–3 mg/kg/d), infliximab (Remicade), topical corticosteroids, or topical calcipotriene (Robinson, 2012; Trivedi, 2018).
Selection of a systemic or topical agent and its dose is directed by disease severity.
As needed, fluid resuscitation, electrolyte correction, and intravenous antibiotics for secondary infections are adjuncts .
Pustular psoriasis of pregnancy typically resolves quickly postpartum, and thus early delivery can be considered individually.
Recurrences are reported in subsequent pregnancies and with menses or oral contraceptive use .
# Erythema Nodosum.
This skin condition reflects subcutaneous fat inflammation and is associated with many disorders, including pregnancy.
Other triggers are infections, sarcoidosis, drugs, Behçet syndrome, inflammatory bowel disease, or malignancy (Mert, 2007; Papagrigoraki, 2010).
Characteristically, tender, red, warm, 1- to 6-cm nodules and plaques develop rapidly on extensor surfaces.
After a few days, lesions flatten, and color evolves like a bruise— from dark red and purple to yellow green.
Constitutional symptoms also may be present.
Initial evaluation and treatment focuses on the underlying etiology.
Symptoms spontaneously resolve in 1 to 6 weeks without scarring but may leave residual hyperpigmentation .
# Pyogenic Granuloma.
This lesion is frequently seen in pregnancy .
Poorly named, pyogenic granuloma is actually a lobular capillary hemangioma.
Pregnancy-associated elevations in angiogenic factors that include vascular endothelial growth factor are implicated (Yuan, 2000, 2004).
It commonly forms on the gingiva, other oral/nasal surfaces, or hand in response to lowgrade local irritation or trauma .
Lesions grow quickly and bleed with minimal provocation.
Active bleeding can be controlled with pressure and application of a silver nitrate stick or Monsel (ferric subsulfate) paste.
These growths often resolve within months postpartum and thus may be observed antepartum.
But, with a symptomatic antepartum growth, a persistent postpartum lesion, or an unclear diagnosis, excision is preferred.
An option is scalpel excision plus suturing, electrosurgical curettage, laser photocoagulation, or cryotherapy.
Oral lesions are best referred to specialists.
Figure 65-4.
Pyogenic granuloma is characterized grossly by a lobulated red growth on a pedunculated or sessile base.
With minimal trauma, these vascular lesions bleed easily.
Reproduced with permission from Dr. Sarah White.
# Miscellaneous Conditions.
Hidradenitis suppurativa is a chronic inflammatory skin disease.
Keratin plugging of hair follicles and recurrent inflammation lead to painful nodules and abscesses that rupture to create sinus tracts.
Hurley stages I–III range from transient, widely spaced inflammatory papules to diffuse involvement with multiple deep sinus tracts between skin abscesses .
For most, symptoms during pregnancy are unchanged or improved (Kromann, 2014; Vossen, 2017).
Treatment aims to decrease cutaneous inflammation and provide antibacterial effects.
For active stage I/II disease, 1-percent clindamycin is topically applied twice daily for 12 weeks .
As alternatives, 0.75-percent metronidazole or 2-percent erythromycin gel are suitable .
For stage II/III disease, a 300-mg clindamycin plus a 300-mg rifampin dose orally twice daily for 10 weeks has evidence-based support .
Adalimumab (Humira) is an FDA-approved biological agent that targets TNF-α and offers a second-line option for advanced-stage disease in pregnancy (Jemec, 2019; Perng, 2017).
Neurofibromatosis lesions are typified by benign cutaneous neurofibromas, café-au-lait spots, axillary and inguinal freckling, benign iris nodules (Lisch nodules), and optic nerve gliomas.
Neurofibromas may grow in size and number during pregnancy (Cesaretti, 2013; Dugoff, 1996).
With neurofibromatosis type 1, higher rates of preeclampsia and preterm birth
complicate pregnancy (Leppävirta, 2017; Terry, 2013).
With type 2, some evidence suggests a risk for preeclampsia .
Prenatal genetic diagnosis is available for both types .
Rosacea fulminans, also known as pyoderma faciale, is rare and typified by facial pustules and coalescing draining sinuses but without comedones.
Its marked presentation usually merits dermatological consultation.
Topical or oral antibiotics are primary treatment, and topical corticosteroids may be added.
Less often, short-course oral corticosteroids or focal surgical drainage is a needed adjunct (Angileri, 2021; Fuentelsaz, 2011; Jarrett, 2010).
Other skin conditions discussed elsewhere in this book are hirsutism and melanoma , cutaneous lupus , hyperpigmentation , and skin lesions seen with infections (Chaps.
67 and 68, p. 1182).
Dermatological Treatment.
Local skin care, oral antihistamines, and topical corticosteroids are commonly used for many dermatoses.
Oral antihistamines are given for pruritus.
Suitable options include first-generation agents such as diphenhydramine (Benadryl), 25 to 50 mg every 6 hours, or chlorpheniramine (Chlor-Trimeton), 4 mg every 6 hours.
Second-generation agents—loratadine (Claritin) 10 mg daily or cetirizine (Zyrtec) 5 or 10 mg daily—may produce less sedation and are also safe for pregnancy.
Numerous topical corticosteroid preparations are available, and in the United States, these are categorized by potency .
For initial treatment of dermatological disorders, low- or moderate-potency agents are preferred.
Low-potency agents include 1-percent hydrocortisone and 0.05percent desonide (DesOwen).
Moderate-potency drugs are 0.1-percent triamcinolone acetonide (Aristocort) and 0.1-percent mometasone furoate (Elocon).
High-potency medications include 0.05-percent betamethasone dipropionate (Diprolene).
Ultrapotent agents, such as 0.05-percent clobetasol propionate (Temovate), are best reserved for refractory disorders and used for only 2 to 4 weeks on small surface areas.
Table 65-2.
Commonly Used Topical Corticosteroids in Pregnancy Mild and moderate strengths are not associated with adverse pregnancy outcomes, whereas high-potency and ultrapotent agents pose a small risk for fetal-growth restriction with large cumulative doses (Chi, 2013, 2015).
Even then, this risk is less than that with oral corticosteroids.
Importantly, with any topical agent, factors that raise systemic absorption include a large surface area treated, compromised epidermal barrier, occlusive dressing, prolonged treatment duration, and coadministration of other topical agents that enhance absorption.
For use in pregnancy and lactation, Murase (2014) and Butler (2014) have compiled tables and evidence-based descriptions of most.
Table 65-3 reflects more commonly encountered agents.
Notable therapeutic agents to avoid during pregnancy include methotrexate, psoralen plus ultraviolet A, mycophenolate mofetil, podophyllin, and systemic retinoids.
These teratogens are discussed in Chapter 8.
Bacterial infections are a potential secondary complication of skin disorders and are treated promptly with oral antimicrobial agents with gram-positive coverage.
Table 65-3.
Some Dermatological Agents and Their Suitability for Pregnancy